This is a talk about sugar and cancer.
هذه محادثة عن السكر والسرطان.
I became interested in sugar when I was in college.
أصبحتُ مهتمة بالسكّر عندما كنت في الكلّية.
Not this kind of sugar.
ليس هذا النوع من السكّر.
It was the sugar that our biology professors taught us about
إنّما كان السكّر الذي علمّنا أساتذة مادة الأحياء عنه
in the context of the coating of your cells.
في سياق الحديث عن غشاء خلاياك.
Maybe you didn't know that your cells are coated with sugar.
ربما لم تكن تعرف أن خلاياك مغلّفة بالسكّر.
And I didn't know that, either,
وأنا أيضًا لم أكن أعلم ذلك،
until I took these courses in college,
حتى تلقّيت تلك المقرّرات في الكلّية،
but back then --
لكن في ذلك الوقت
and this was in, let's just call it the 1980s --
وكان هذا في .. لنسمّيها فقط الثمانينيّات
people didn't know much about why our cells are coated with sugar.
لم يكن الناس يعلمون الكثير عن سبب كون خلايانا مغلّفة بالسكّر.
And when I dug through my notes, what I noticed I had written down
وعندما فتّشتُ في ملاحظاتي، لاحظت أني قد كتبت
is that the sugar coating on our cells is like the sugar coating
أن غلاف السكّر على خلايانا أشبه بطبقة السكّر
on a peanut M and M.
على حبة الفول السوداني M&amp;M's.
And people thought the sugar coating on our cells
وكان الناس يعتقدون أن غلاف السكّر على خلايانا
was like a protective coating
بمثابة غطاء واقٍ
that somehow made our cells stronger or tougher.
يجعلُ خلايانا أقوى أو أصلب.
But we now know, many decades later,
لكننا نعلم الآن، بعد عقود عديدة،
that it's much more complicated than that,
أن الأمر أكثر تعقيدًا بكثير من هذا،
and that the sugars on our cells are actually very complex.
وأن السكّريّات على خلايانا هي في الواقع معقّدة جدًّا.
And if you could shrink yourself down to a little miniature airplane
وإذا أمكنك أن تنكمشَ لتصير بحجم طائرة مصَغّرَة
and fly right along the surface of your cells,
وتُحلّقَ تمامًا بمحاذاة سطح خلاياك،
it might look something like this --
فربما يبدو شيئًا من هذا القبيل؛
with geographical features.
بما له من معالِمَ جغرافيّة.
And now, the complex sugars are these trees and bushes --
والآن، هذه السكّريّات المعقّدة هي تلك الأشجارُ والشجيّراتُ
weeping willows that are swaying in the wind
أشجارُ الصفصاف الباكي التي تتمايل مع الريح
and moving with the waves.
وتتحرّك مع الموج.
And when I started thinking about all these complex sugars
وعندما بدأتُ بالتفكير في كلّ هذه السكّريّات المعقّدة
that are like this foliage on our cells,
التي تشبه أوراق الشجر فوق خلايانا،
it became one of the most interesting problems that I encountered
صارت واحدة من أكثر المسائل المثيرة للاهتمام التي قابلتُها
as a biologist and also as a chemist.
كعالمة أحياء وأيضًا كعالمة كيميائية.
And so now we tend to think about the sugars
ولذا نميل الآن إلى التفكير في السكّريّات
that are populating the surface of our cells
التي تستوطن سطح خلايانا
as a language.
باعتبارها لُغَة.
They have a lot of information stored in their complex structures.
هذه السُكّريّات تحوي العديد من المعلومات مخزّنةً في تركيباتها المعقّدة.
But what are they trying to tell us?
لكن ما الذي تحاول إخبارنا به؟
I can tell you that we do know some information
يمكنني إخباركم أننا نعرف بعض المعلومات
that comes from these sugars,
التي تأتي من هذه السُكّريّات،
and it's turned out already to be incredibly important
وتبيّن بالفعل أنّها مهمّة بشكل لا يُصدَّق
in the world of medicine.
في عالَم الطب.
For example, one thing your sugars are telling us
على سبيل المثال، أحد الأشياء التي تخبرنا بها سُكّريّاتك
is your blood type.
هو فصيلة دمك.
So your blood cells, your red blood cells, are coated with sugars,
إذن خلايا دمك، خلايا دمك الحمراء، مغلّفة بالسكرّيّات،
and the chemical structures of those sugars determine your blood type.
والتراكيب الكيميائية لهذه السكّريّات تحدّد فصيلة دمك.
So for example, I know that I am blood type O.
لذا مثلاً أنا أعلم أن فصيلة دمي O.
How many people are also blood type O?
كم عدد الناس الذين يحملون الفصيلة O أيضًا؟
Put your hands up.
ارفعوا أيديكم.
It's a pretty common one,
إنها فصيلة شائعة جدًّا،
so when so few hands go up, either you're not paying attention
لذا عندما يرفع القليل أيديهم، فهذا يعني أنّكم إمّا غير منتبهين
or you don't know your blood type, and both of those are bad.
أو لا تعلمون فصيلة دمكم، وهذا سيء في كلتا الحالتين.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But for those of you who share the blood type O with me,
لكن بالنسبة لهولاء الذين يشاركوني الفصيلة O،
what this means is that we have this chemical structure
ما يعنيه هذا هو أنّنا لدينا هذا التركيب الكيميائي
on the surface of our blood cells:
على سطح خلايا دمنا:
three simple sugars linked together to make a more complex sugar.
ثلاثة سكّريّات بسيطة مرتبطة معًا لتكوّن سكّرًا أكثر تعقيدًا.
And that, by definition, is blood type O.
وهذه هي فصيلة الدم O حسب التعريف.
Now, how many people are blood type A?
الآن، كم عدد الناس الذين يحملون الفصيلة A؟
Right here.
ها هنا.
That means you have an enzyme in your cells
هذا يعني أن لديكم إنزيمًا في خلاياكم
that adds one more building block,
والذي يضيف وحدة بناء إضافيّة،
that red sugar,
ذلك السكّر الأحمر،
to build a more complex structure.
ليبني تركيبًا أكثر تعقيدًا.
And how many people are blood type B?
وكم عدد الناس الذين يحملون فصيلة الدم B؟
Quite a few.
عدد لا بأس به.
You have a slightly different enzyme than the A people,
لديكم إنزيم مختلف قليلاً عن أصحاب الفصيلة A
so you build a slightly different structure,
لذا تبنون تركيبًا مختلفًا قليلاً،
and those of you that are AB
أمّا أولئك أصحاب الفصيلة AB
have the enzyme from your mother, the other enzyme from your father,
فتحصلون على الإنزيم الأوّل من أمِّكم، والإنزيم الآخَر من أبيكم،
and now you make both of these structures in roughly equal proportions.
وتصنعون كلا التركيبين بنِسَب متساوية تقريبًا.
And when this was figured out,
وعندما تمّ اكتشاف ذلك،
which is now back in the previous century,
وكان هذا في القرن الماضي بالنسبة للآن،
this enabled one of the most important medical procedures in the world,
أفسح الطريق لواحدة من أهمّ العمليّات الطبّية في العالم،
which, of course, is the blood transfusion.
وهي بالطبع نقل الدم.
And by knowing what your blood type is,
وبمعرفة فصيلة دمك،
we can make sure, if you ever need a transfusion,
يمكننا أن نتأكّد -إن احتجت لنقل دم في أي وقت-
that your donor has the same blood type,
أنّ المانح لديه نفس فصيلة دمك،
so that your body doesn't see foreign sugars,
حتى لا يرى جسمُك سكّرّيات غريبة
which it wouldn't like and would certainly reject.
لن يحبّها وقطعًا سيرفضها.
What else are the sugars on the surface of your cells trying to tell us?
ماذا أيضًا تحاول السكّريّات على سطح خلاياك إخبارك به؟
Well, those sugars might be telling us that you have cancer.
حسنًا، هذه السكّريّات ربما تخبرنا أنك مصاب بالسرطان.
So a few decades ago,
لذا منذ عقود قليلة مضت،
correlations began to emerge from the analysis of tumor tissue.
بدأت تبرز العلاقات بينهما من تحليل نسيج الأورام.
And the typical scenario is a patient would have a tumor detected,
والسيناريو النموذجي هو أن يُرصَد الورمُ عند المريض
and the tissue would be removed in a biopsy procedure
ويتمّ إزالة عيّنة من النسيج بإجراء خزعة
and then sent down to a pathology lab
ثم ترسل العيّنة إلى معمل الباثولوجي (علم الأمراض)
where that tissue would be analyzed to look for chemical changes
حيثُ يتمّ تحليل النسيج بحثًا عن التغيّرات الكيميائية
that might inform the oncologist about the best course of treatment.
التي قد تدلّ اختصاصي الأورام على أفضل مسار للعلاج.
And what was discovered from studies like that
والذي اكتُشِفَ من دراسات كهذه
is that the sugars have changed
أن السكّريّات كانت قد تغيّرت
when the cell transforms from being healthy to being sick.
أثناء تحوّل الخليّة من الصحّة إلى المرض.
And those correlations have come up again and again and again.
وهذه العلاقات ظهرت مرارًا وتكرارًا.
But a big question in the field has been: Why?
لكن سؤالاً كبيرًا في المجال كان: لماذا؟
Why do cancers have different sugars? What's the importance of that?
لماذا تحوي السرطانات سكّريّات مختلفة؟ ما أهميّة ذلك؟
Why does it happen, and what can we do about it if it does turn out
لماذا يحدث ذلك، وما الذي يمكننا فعله بهذا الخصوص إن تبيّن
to be related to the disease process?
أن لذلك علاقة بعملية المرض؟
So, one of the changes that we study
لذا واحد من التغيّرات التي ندرسها
is an increase in the density of a particular sugar
هو الزيادة في كثافة سكّر معيّن
that's called sialic acid.
يسمّى حمض السياليك.
And I think this is going to be one of the most important sugars
وأعتقد أنه سيصبح أحد أهمّ السكّريّات
of our times,
في عصرنا،
so I would encourage everybody to get familiar with this word.
لذا أشجّع كل شخص أن يعتاد هذه الكلمة.
Sialic acid is not the kind of sugar that we eat.
حمض السياليك ليس ذاك النوع من السكّر الذي يؤكل.
Those are different sugars.
هذه سكّريّات مختلفة.
This is a kind of sugar that is actually found
هذا نوع من السّكر الذي يُوجَد في الواقع
at certain levels on all of the cells in your body.
بمستويّات محدّدة على كلّ خلايا جسمك.
It's actually quite common on your cells.
في الواقع هو شائع إلى حد ما على سطح خلاياك.
But for some reason,
لكن لسبب ما،
cancer cells, at least in a successful, progressive disease,
فإن الخلايا السرطانية -على الأقل حين يكون المرض متمكنًا ويتفاقم-
tend to have more sialic acid
تميل إلى امتلاك المزيد من حمض السياليك
than a normal, healthy cell would have.
أكثر مما تمتلكه خليّة عادية وسليمة.
And why?
ولماذا؟
What does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
Well, what we've learned
حسنًا، ما عرفناه
is that it has to do with your immune system.
هو أن لذلك علاقة بجهازكم المناعي.
So let me tell you a little bit about the importance of your immune system
لذا دعوني أخبركم قليلاً عن أهميّة جهازكم المناعي
in cancer.
في السرطان.
And this is something that's, I think, in the news a lot these days.
وهذا الموضوع -على ما أظنّ- يتردّد في الأخبار بكثرة هذه الأيام
You know, people are starting to become familiar with the term
كما تعلمون، بدأ الناس يعتادون مصطلح
"cancer immune therapy."
"علاج السرطان المناعي."
And some of you might even know people
وبعضكم حتى قد يعرفون أُناسًا
who are benefiting from these very new ways of treating cancer.
يستفيدون من هذه الطرق الحديثة جدًا في علاج السرطان.
What we now know is that your immune cells,
ما نعرفه الآن هو أن خلاياك المناعية،
which are the white blood cells coursing through your bloodstream,
التي هي خلايا الدم البيضاء المنطلقة عبر مجرى الدم.
protect you on a daily basis from things gone bad --
تحميك بصفة يومية من الأشياء الفاسدة
including cancer.
بما فيهم السرطان.
And so in this picture,
ولذا في هذه الصورة،
those little green balls are your immune cells,
تلك الكُرات الخضراء الصغيرة هي خلاياك المناعية،
and that big pink cell is a cancer cell.
وتلك الخليّة الكبيرة ورديّة اللون هي خليّة سرطانية.
And these immune cells go around and taste all the cells in your body.
وهذه الخلايا المناعية تتجوّل وتتذوّق كل خلايا جسمك.
That's their job.
تلك هي وظيفتها.
And most of the time, the cells taste OK.
ومعظم الوقت، يكون مذاق الخلايا مقبولاً.
But once in a while, a cell might taste bad.
لكن من وقت للآخر، قد يوجد خليّة مذاقها سيء.
Hopefully, that's the cancer cell,
لنأمل أن تلك هي الخليّة السرطانية،
and when those immune cells get the bad taste,
وعندما تدرك الخلايا المناعية ذاك المذاق السيئ،
they launch an all-out strike and kill those cells.
تشنّ هجومًا شاملاً وتقتل هذه الخلايا.
So we know that.
لذا هذا ما نعرفه.
We also know that if you can potentiate that tasting,
ونعرف أيضًا أنه إن كان بمقدورك تعزيز ذلك التذوّق،
if you can encourage those immune cells to actually take a big old bite
إذا أمكنك حثّ تلك الخلايا المناعية على أخذ قضمة أكبر فعليًا
out of a cancer cell,
من الخلية السرطانية،
you get a better job protecting yourself from cancer every day
فأنت تقوم بعمل جيّد في الحفاظ على نفسك من السرطان كل يوم
and maybe even curing a cancer.
وربما حتى الشفاء منه.
And there are now a couple of drugs out there in the market
وهناك الآن نوعان من الأدوية في السوق
that are used to treat cancer patients
يُستخدمان لعلاج مرضى السرطان
that act exactly by this process.
ويعملان بالضبط بهذه الآليّة.
They activate the immune system
ينشّطان الجهاز المناعي
so that the immune system can be more vigorous
ليُصبح أكثر قوّة
in protecting us from cancer.
في حمايتنا من السرطان.
In fact, one of those drugs
أحد هذين العلاجين في الحقيقة
may well have spared President Jimmy Carter's life.
ربما يكون قد أنقذ حياة الرئيس جيمي كارتر.
Do you remember, President Carter had malignant melanoma
هل تتذكّرون، كان الرئيس كارتر مُصابًا بسرطان الجلد الخبيث
that had metastasized to his brain,
الذي انتشر إلى مخّه،
and that diagnosis is one that is usually accompanied by numbers
وهذا التشخيص يكون مصحوبًا عادةً بأرقام
like "months to live."
مثل "لم يتبقّى في حياته سوى شهور."
But he was treated with one of these new immune-stimulating drugs,
لكنّه عولج بأحد هذه الأدوية الجديدة المنشّطة للمناعة،
and now his melanoma appears to be in remission,
ويبدو الآن أن سرطان جلده في تراجع،
which is remarkable,
وهو ما يعدّ مثيرًا للإعجاب،
considering the situation only a few years ago.
بالنظر إلى الوضع قبل عدة سنوات فقط.
In fact, it's so remarkable
في الحقيقة، هذا مثير للإعجاب جدًا
that provocative statements like this one:
لدرجة أن الناس بدأوا يردّدون عبارات حماسية مثل:
"Cancer is having a penicillin moment," people are saying,
"بداية النهاية للسرطان"
with these new immune therapy drugs.
بفضل أدوية العلاج المناعي الجديدة تلك.
I mean, that's an incredibly bold thing to say about a disease
أقصد أن ذلك شيء جريء لقوله عن مرضٍ
which we've been fighting for a long time
كنا نحاربه لفترة طويلة
and mostly losing the battle with.
وفي أغلب الأحيان نخسر المعركة أمامه.
So this is very exciting.
لذا هذا مثير جدًّا.
Now what does this have to do with sugars?
الآن ما علاقة هذا بالسكّريّات؟
Well, I'll tell you what we've learned.
حسنًا، سأخبركم ما عرفناه.
When an immune cell snuggles up against a cancer cell to take a taste,
عندما تلتصق الخليّة المناعية بأحد الخلايا السرطانيّة لتتذوّقها،
it's looking for signs of disease,
فإنها تبحث عن علامات المرض،
and if it finds those signs,
وإذا وجدت هذه العلامات،
the cell gets activated and it launches a missile strike and kills the cell.
فإنها تنشط وتشنّ هجومًا صاروخيًّا وتقتل الخليّة السرطانية.
But if that cancer cell has a dense forest of that sugar, sialic acid,
لكن إذا كان لدى الخلية السرطانية غابة كثيفة من ذاك السكّر-حمض السياليك-
well, it starts to taste pretty good.
حسنًا، يتحسّن مذاقُها إلى حدّ ما.
And there's a protein on immune cells that grabs the sialic acid,
وهناك بروتين على الخلايا المناعيّة ليُمسِك بحمض السياليك
and if that protein gets held at that synapse
وعندما يُمسك البروتين بالحمض عند موضع التشابك
between the immune cell and the cancer cell,
بين الخليّة المناعيّة والخليّة السرطانيّة،
it puts that immune cell to sleep.
فإنه يأمر هذه الخليّة المناعية أن تخلُد إلى النوم.
The sialic acids are telling the immune cell,
أي أن حمض السياليك يخبر الخليّة المناعيّة،
Look somewhere else."
ابحثي في مكان آخر."
So in other words,
لذا بكلمات أخرى،
as long as our cells are wearing a thick coat of sialic acid,
طالما ترتدي خلايانا معطفًا سميكًا من حمض السياليك،
they look fabulous, right?
فإنها تبدو رائعة، صحيح؟
It's amazing.
هذا مدهش.
And what if you could strip off that coat
وماذا لو خلعْتَ ذلك المعطف
and take that sugar away?
وأزلْتَ ذلك السكّر بعيدًا؟
Well, your immune system
حسنًا، جهازك المناعي
might be able to see that cancer cell for what it really is:
سيكون قادرًا ربّما على رؤية الخليّة السرطانية على حقيقتها:
something that needs to be destroyed.
شيئًا لا بد من تدميره.
And so this is what we're doing in my lab.
ولذا هذا ما نفعله في معملي.
We're developing new medicines
نطوّر أدوية جديدة
that are basically cell-surface lawnmowers --
تعمل بالأساس كجزّازات عشب على سطح الخليّة
molecules that go down to the surface of these cancer cells
حيث إنها عبارة عن جزيئات تهبط على سطح هذه الخلايا السرطانيّة
and just cut off those sialic acids,
وتقوم فقط بقطع جزيئات حمض السياليك،
so that the immune system can reach its full potential
ليستطيع الجهاز المناعي أن يصل لكامل قوّته
in eliminating those cancer cells from our body.
في إقصاء هذه الخلايا السرطانيّة من جسدنا.
So in closing,
لذا في الختام،
let me just remind you again:
دعوني فقط أذكّركم مرة أخرى:
your cells are coated with sugars.
خلاياكم مغلّفة بالسكّريّات.
The sugars are telling cells around that cell
هذه السكّريّات تخبر الخلايا المناعيّة عن هذه الخليّة
whether the cell is good or bad.
ما إذا كانت جيّدة أم سيّئة.
And that's important,
وهذا مهمّ،
because our immune system needs to leave the good cells alone.
لأن جهازنا المناعي يحتاج أن يترك الخلايا الجيّدة وحدها.
Otherwise, we'd have autoimmune diseases.
وإلّا سنصاب بأمراض المناعة الذاتية.
But once in a while, cancers get the ability
لكن أحيانًا تكتسب السرطانات القدرة
to express these new sugars.
على تصنيع هذه السكّريّات الجديدة.
And now that we understand
وبما أننا نفهم الآن
how those sugars mesmerize the immune system,
كيف تنوّم هذه السكّريّات جهازنا المناعي مغناطيسيًا،
we can come up with new medicines to wake up those immune cells,
يمكننا أن نأتي بأدوية جديدة لإيقاظِ تلك الخلايا المناعيّة،
tell them, "Ignore the sugars, eat the cell
وإخبارِها "تجاهلي السكّريّات، التهمي الخليّة
and have a delicious snack, on cancer."
وتناولي وجبة خفيفة لذيذة من السرطان."
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)